Guide to the Montana State Prison records 1864-1974
Montana Historical Society
Montana State Prison records
1864-1974
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 197
Montana State Prison.
70 linear feet
This collection consists of records of the Montana State Prison (1869-1974), the Board of Pardons (1890-1965), the Board of Prison Commissioners (1890-1962), and the United States Penitentiary, Montana Territory, including materials such as prisoner description sheets, prisoner receipt and discharge registers, minutes, reports, etc.
Representative John N. Rodgers introduced HB Memorial 7 in December 1866 that sought federal funds for a territorial penitentiary in Montana. In January 1867 funding was approved and the penitentiary opened in Deer Lodge in July 1871. It was relinquished to Montana Territory in 1873, and taken over by the federal government once again in 1874. The penitentiary became a state institution in 1889, when Montana achieved statehood.
The state contracted with former prison guard Frank Conley and Colonel Thomas McTague to operate the penitentiary from 1890 to 1908, with Conley as warden. In 1909 the state hired Conley as warden, a position he held until 1921. Conley instituted an extensive trusty program in which many prisoners worked outside the prison walls. Prison work crews built roads in western Montana and constructed buildings at the Montana State Hospital for the Insane and the Montana State Tuberculosis Sanitarium, as well as making many improvements to the prison itself. In 1921 Governor Joseph Dixon initiated an investigation of Conley's alleged use of state monies for personal gain; this investigation led to Conley's dismissal.
Conditions at the prison deteriorated in the decades that followed Conley's dismissal. The trusty program was largely abandoned due to the depressed economy and the concomitant protest by free labor against prisoners working outside the prison. Additionally, few industries had been developed within the prison, leaving many inmates idle. Overcrowding and the decay of the physical plant contributed to poor living conditions at the prison.
In 1957 an investigation of prison conditions conducted by Kenyon J. Scudder reported appalling and potentially explosive conditions at the prison. Later that year a "disturbance" did occur during which hostages were taken. A large scale riot occurred in 1959. The prison was made part of the Department of Institutions in 1963. A new prison was constructed in 1979 outside of Deer Lodge.
The Board of Territorial Prison Commissioners (later the Board of Prison Commissioners) was established in 1867, consisting of three elected members holding office for two years. The commissioners had "full and exclusive control over all the territorial prison grounds, buildings, prisoners, prison labor, prison property and all other things belonging or pertaining to said prison," and established "rules, regulations and by-laws" to govern the prison. The commissioners met every three months. An 1893 law removed prisoners from the commissioners' control, empowered the Board to appoint the warden, and established the Board as consisting of the governor, the secretary of state, and the attorney general, with two members constituting a quorum. In 1907 the Board was given the power to approve or disapprove parole for prisoners recommended by the governor. In 1913 the governor was given the power to appoint the warden, and the Board was given jurisdiction over persons receiving suspended sentences. In 1955 the Board's jurisdiction over paroles and suspended sentences was delegated to the State Board of Pardons. Legislation establishing the Board of State Prison Commissioners was not included in the 1972 constitution; the Board was formally abolished in 1974.
The State Board of Pardons was established in 1891, consisting of the secretary of state, the attorney general, and the state auditor. The Board was required to convene if the governor granted a pardon, remitted a fine or forfeiture, or commuted a punishment. The Board would then cause a notice of a hearing concerning the case to be published in a newspaper in the county in which the crime was committed and notify the concerned county attorney, district judge, and sheriff. Subsequent to the hearing the Board would file its decision with the secretary of state. In 1955 the Board membership was changed to three members appointed by the governor to terms of six years. The appointees were given the responsibility of administering the executive clemency, probation, and parole system. The Board was made part of the Department of Institutions in 1971.
This collection is divided into four subgroups: Montana State Prison Records (1881-1974); Board of State Prison Commissioners Records (1890-1962); State Board of Pardons Records (1890-1965); and the United States Penitentiary, Montana Territory Records (1864-1878).
The records of the Montana State Prison are divided into five series. The general correspondence (1891-1916) contains letters between Frank Conley and Thomas McTague and the governor, the clerk of the Board of Examiners, and two suppliers to the prison. The outgoing correspondence (1909-1921) of Conley and McTague pertains to inmates (paroles, pardons, behavior, time served, restoration to citizenship, escapes, work camps, sale of goods produced by prisoners, etc.), supplies, prison employment, penology, personal business of Conley and McTague, etc. The financial records (1893-1963) include cash books, general ledgers, journals, prisoner accounts with Deer Lodge and prison stores, voucher registers, etc. The bulk of the prisoner records (1881-1974) consists of prison description sheets which include each prisoners' vital statistics, and information about the crime committed, the sentence received, and a list of past crimes. The prisoner records also include lists of a conduct record; criminal charges against former Montana State Prison inmates; lists of prisoners received and discharged; a medical treatment record; lists of prisoners who were pardoned, paroled, and received suspended sentences, diminished sentences, and restoration of citizenship; and prison population statements.
The records of the State Board of Pardons include minutes (1880-1926), prisoner records (1892-1922), and miscellany (1963, 1965). The minutes are primarily approvals of paroles. The prisoner records are correspondence and documents relating to specific prisoners' pardons.
The records of the Board of State Prison Commissioners are divided into seven series. The general correspondence (1905-1929) consists of correspondence of the clerk of the Board. The hearings series (1957) consists of a transcript of a hearing concerning an investigation of conditions at the prison. The legal documents (1907, 1927) consist of an agreement for the purchase of cement and an easement granted to a railroad. The minutes (1890-1962) primarily concern the approval of paroles, the discharge of prisoners, the termination of sentences, return of prisoners for violation of parole, transfer of prisoners to the State Hospital for the Insane, etc. For some years (1910-1927,1949-1954) there is a separate run of minutes that deals exclusively with paroles. There is some discussion of procedures, investigations, etc. The prisoner records (1913-1955) consist of suspended sentence orders. The reports series (1960) consists of a report by the Prison Advisory Board concerning prison industries. The miscellany series (1959, undated) includes blank forms, procedural guidelines, and interviews with prisoners relating to the approval of "good time".
The records of the United States Penitentiary, Montana Territory, are divided into six series. The general correspondence series (1875) consists of correspondence sent by W. F. Wheeler concerning housing prisoners. The incoming correspondence series (1874-1876) consists of correspondence received by W. F. Wheeler concerning housing prisoners and leasing space in court rooms. The financial records series (1886-1889) consists of an expense journal kept R. S. Kelley. The legal documents series consists of leases, memoranda of agreement and miscellany concerning housing prisoners, operating the prison and construction of the prison. The reports series (1873, 1878, undated) consists of reports of the Directors, the Physician, the Warden, and the U.S. Grand Jury. The miscellany series (1868-1878) consists of documents regarding the construction of the prison, inventories and rules and regulations. Restriction: Prisoner description sheets are restricted from public use due to their fragility. An archivist can search these sheets and provide the researcher with a receival date at the prison. This date will allow the researcher to find the prisoner description sheet on State Microfilm 36, where the description sheets are arranged by date received at the prison. Researchers are advised to provide the archivist with all possible variations of the prisoner's name.
The collection is arranged by subgroup and then by series. Subgroups include: 1. Montana State Prison, 2. Board of Pardons, 3. Board of State Prison Commissioners, and 4. United States Penitentiary. Montana Territory.
Collection is open for research. Use of the prisoner description sheets is restricted due to their fragile condition. An archivist can search these sheets and provide the researcher with a receival date at the prison. This date will allow the researcher to find the prisoner description sheet on State Microfilm 36, where the description sheets are arranged by date received at the prison. Researchers are advised to provide the archivist with all possible variations of the prisoner's name.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Genealogy--Montana--Sources.; Law enforcement--Montana.; Pardon--Montana.; Parole--Montana.; Prison riots--Montana.; Prisoners--Montana.; Prisons--Montana.
Deer Lodge (Mont.)--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Montana State Prison
  - General Correspondence
    - Frank Conley and Thomas McTague (includes letters to and from the Governor, the clerk of the Board of Examiner, and various suppliers of goods), 1891-1916 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Frank Conley (re restoration of citizenship; escapees; bridles made and sold by inmates; inquiries about specific inmates from family and friends; supply orders; business contracts and personal business), 1909, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 1/2-1/6)
    - Frank Conley (re restoration of citizenship; escapees; bridles made and sold by inmates; inquiries about specific inmates from family and friends; supply orders; business contracts and person business), 1910-1915, 1919, 1921 (Volume 1-16)
    - Frank Conley (re restoration of citizenship; escapees; bridles made and sold by inmates; inquiries about specific inmates from family and friends; supply orders; business contracts and personal business), 1917-1919 (Box-folder 2/1-2/5)
    - Frank Conley (re restoration of citizenship; escapees; bridles made and sold by inmates; inquiries about specific inmates from family and friends; supply orders; business contracts and personal business; recommendations to women regarding whether prisoners would make good husband; Industrial Workers of the World; construction), 1919-1921 (Box-folder 3/1-3/4)
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book, 1910 November - 1912 November (Volume 17)
    - Cash receipts, 1922-1925 (Volume 18)
    - Day book, prisoner store accounts, 1912-1920 (Volume 19-25)
    - Day book, prisoner accounts with Gem Grocery Co., 1926-1934 (Volume 26-27)
    - Day book, prisoner accounts with Milwaukee Market, 1925-1931 (Volume 28-31)
    - Day book, prisoner accounts with Whitworth Drug Store, 1925-1927 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Day book, prisoner accounts with Woods Drug Company, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - General ledger, 1893-1896 (Volume 32)
    - General ledger (materials removed from Vol. 32), 1893-1896 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - General ledger, 1912-1917, 1925-1951 (Volume 33-35)
    - General ledger, 1945-1963 (Box-folder OVERSIZE 89/1)
    - Journal and index, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Journal, November-December 1921 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Quarterly statements to the federal government for the care of prisoners committed to the Montana State Prison, 1908-1909, 1910 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Receipts and vouchers for county sheriffs'' deliveries of prisoners to state prison, 1909-1912 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Voucher register, 1913-1922 (Volume 36)
  - Prisoner Records
    - Criminal charges against former inmates, 1927-1937 (Box-folder 3/12-3/14)
    - Criminal charges against former inmates, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 4/1-4/3)
    - Conduct records, 1892-1901 (Volume 37)
    - Descriptive lists of prisoners received (identical information to that recorded on prisoner description sheets, but also includes number of days a prisoner was punished and the mode of punishment), 1912-1921 (Volume 38)
    - Medical treatment record, 1892-1895 (Volume 39)
    - Monthly discharge lists, 1931-1934 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Pardon records, 1897-1913 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Pardons, diminished sentences, restorations to citizenship, 1895-1897 (Box-folder OVERSIZE 89/2)
    - Pardons, diminished sentences, restorations to citizenship, 1898-1902 (Volume 40)
    - Parole lists, 1927-1943 (Box-folder 4/6-4/9)
    - Parole lists, 1944-1950 (Box-folder OVERSIZE 89/3)
    - Parole records, 1907-1916 (Volume 41)
    - Alphabetical index to Vol. 41, 1916 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Parole record (also includes paroles from the Montana State Reform School, 1911-1915; paroles from the Montana State Hospital, 1914; suspended sentences by judges of district courts, 1913-1922; and violators of parole or suspended sentence, 1913-1921) (Volume 42)
    - Parole record, 1913-1922 (Volume 43)
    - Population statements, 1915-1959 (Box-folder 4/11-4/18)
    - Population statements, 1960 (Box-folder OVERSIZE 89/4)
    - Population statements, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Prison Cemetery inmate burials, 1881-1973 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Prisoner description cards: John Aaboe, John Aakre, C.E. Abbie, Charles Abbot, Frank Abbott, Alfred Abel, D.J. Abel, Harry Abel, Lawrence Abel, Robert Abel, Joe Abell, E. Guy Abernathy, Jay Acebedo, Rolin Acherman, William Acker, Charles Ackerley, William Ackerman, Voy Ackroyd, Leo Acosta, John Adair, Alex Adams, Alfred Adams, Charles Adams, David Adams, Earl Adams, Edward Adams, Frank Adams, James Adams, Jesse Adams, John Adams, Joseph Adams, Orville Adams, William Adams, Wilbur Adams, Kermit Adamson, Earl Addison, Frank Addler, George Ade, Louis Adler, Joseph Adrian, Walle Aemtoft, Ben Aerts, Fred Age, Sam Agee, Tommy Aglular, Antonio Aguilar, Herman Aho, Kenneth Ahrenkiel, Howard Ahrens, Clarence Aichele, August Aiello, Frank Aikens, George Aikens, Jack Aiker, William Aiman, Francis Aims Back, Charles Ainsworth, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Prisoner description cards: Archie Aker, Clifford Akerill, Norman Akerill, Hugh Akers, John Akers, Orville Akers, William Akin, Desiderio Alarcon, Harry Albert, Alber Albertson, George Albertson (Charles Busetta), William Albertson, Francisco Albi, H.R. Albrecht, Juan Alcatar, Robert Alcorn, Joe Aldaco, Emanuel Aldena, B.E. Alderman, Ben Aldridge, Thomas Aldridged, Tom Alefteras, A.C. Alexander, Albert Alexander, Carl Alexander, Donald Alexander, Eugene Alexander, Paul Alexander, Peter Alexander, Roy Alexander, William Alexander, Anthony Alexandrowski, Lynn Alexis, Inonsencio Alfara, John Alguire, Edward Alimendinger, T.C. Allan, Edward Allard, Clarence Alleman, Albert Allen, Carl Allen, Charles Allen Frank Allen, Garnet Allen, Gene Allen, George Allen, Glenn Allen, Harry Allen, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Prisoner description cards: Jack Allen (James Clark), James Allen, Jim Allen (Earl Powell), Joe Allen, John Allen, Joseph Allen, Murl Allen, P.E. Allen, R.T. Allen, Roy Allen (Hugh Shivley), Russell Allen, Sam Allen, Scott Allen, Ted Allen (Red Von Hoeren), Theodore Allen, Tom Allen, W.J. Allen, William Allen (Bernard Swift Williams), Robert Alley, Thomas Alley, John Alliey, James Allison, Murphy Allran, Howard Allum, Vernon Allyn, Raymond Allyson, Rafael Almendarez, Healy Aloir, Joe Alonzo, Russell Alsop, Arnold Alsup, George Alton, Joe Alvaraz, Juan Alvarez, Agapito Alvary, Joseph Alvers, Bert Alyea, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Prisoner description cards: James Ambrose, Clifford Amdahl, Francis Ameline, Henry Amend, Neil Amerman, Edwin Ames, Marvin Ames, Angel Amicay, Mervin Amick, Fred Ammeline (Alfred Hamelin), Emmet Amos, William Amrin, John Amyotte, Louis Amzevine, A.J. Anaker, August Ancker, Ace Anderson, Albert Anderson, Alfred Anderson, Andrew Anderson, Arthur Anderson (Bert Buller), Carl Anderson, Chester Anderson, Claude Anderson, David Anderson, Donald Anderson, Elmer Anderson, Erick Anderson, Francis Anderson, Frank Anderson, George Anderson, Harold Anderson (Harold McManus, Albert Jennings, Harry Anderson), Jack Anderson (George Wilson, Jack Horst, Jack Wilson), John Anderson, Julius Anderson (Julius), 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Prisoner description cards: K.A.R. Anderson, Leonard Anderson, Lester Anderson, Martin Anderson, Nels Anderson, Norman Anderson, Oliver Anderson, Paul Anderson, Pete Anderson, Roy Anderson, Vernon Anderson, W.E. Anderson, W.H. Anderson, Walter Anderson, William Anderson, Charles Andrew, Fred Andrew, Norman Andrew, Steve Andrewpenkl, James Andrews, Louis Andriopoulos, Lee Andrus, R.L. Andrus, Tony Aneso, Peter Anest, Thurman Anglin, Rafael Anguiana, Genaro Anguiano, Frank Antonich, Carl Applegate, Joe Argon, Julian Aranda, Virgil Archbell, William Archibald, Joe Archuleto, John Arcoga, Sylva Arenz (Arthur Arenz), Pablo Ariaz, Stark Arklow, James Arlington, O.L. Armour, A.S. Armstrong, Alva Armstrong, Barney Armstrong, Cyrus Armstrong, David Armstrong, Dean Armstrong, Dolphus Armstrong, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Prisoner description cards: Frank Armstrong, George Armstrong, Le Roy Armstrong, Lester Armstrong, Roy Armstrong, William Armstrong, Helmer Arness, A.H. Arnold, Albert Arnold, Arthur Arnold, Ben Arnold, Charles Arnold, Frankie Arnold, Harry Arnold, John Arnold, W.J. Arnold, William Arnoldy, Ramon Aronbarra, Victor Arrison, Charles Arseneau (Harry Patterson), Lester Arthur, George Asbury, Leo Asbury, Marvin Ash, Violet Ashe, Marvin Ashe, Harry Asher, Mary Asher, Mary Azure, Guy Ashley, Harless Ashley, J.W. Ashely, Louis Ashley, William Ashley, Charles Ashlock, Jack Ashton, Arthur Asp, George Assiminis, Harry Atchison, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Prisoner description cards: Ernest Atencio, J.C. Atherton, J.E. Atkins, Alexander Atkinson, George Atkinson, George Atwood, Robert Atwood, Frank Augustine, Marvin Aullman, Fred Aurrah, Martin Aus, Perry Aus, Benjamin Austin, Ed Austin, James Austin (Jake Austin), Lee Austin, Paul Austin, Buck Avery, Joe Avila, John Avouris, Earl Awes, Thomas Ayers, Howard Ayrea, Jimmie Ayers, John Ayers, Vincent Ayers, Willis Ayers, Pat Azura, Baptiste Azure, Bill Azure, Glen Azure, John Azure, Joseph Azure, Max Azure, Richard Azure, Vern Azure, Walter Azure, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Prisoner description cards: Kenneth Baatz, Lester Babb, Clarence Babcock, M.M. Babcock, Reuben Babcock, Max Baber, Paul Babick, Joe Bachmeier, George Backer, George Backman, Blacop Backroch, Ralph Badger, Mike Badorek, George Baggs, J. Bagley, W.E. Bagley, W.J. Bagley, Jospeh Bahm, Gordon Bahr, Betty Bailey, C.L. Bailey, Don Bailey, Fred Bailey, George Bailey, Hammond Bailey, Irene Bailey, Jess Bailey, Joseph Bailey, Lee Bailey, M.E. Bailey, Roger Bailey, William Bailey, Harry Bain, Ora Bain, Nelson Baird, Theodore Baird, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Prisoner description cards: Ben Baker, Dick Baker, Dolly Baker, Frank Baker (Frank Blacker), Fred Baker, Frederick Baker, George Baker, H.D. Baker, Homer Baker, Jack Baker, Janes Baker, Jim Baker, John Baker, Joseph Baker, Leo Baker, Louis Baker, Orville Baker, Raleigh Baker, Wallace Baker, Walter Baker, Willie Baker, H.A. Baker, Hans Bakke, Frank Balbi, Jan Balcer, Ezra Balcom, Leo Balcom, Harry Baldwin, James Baldwin, Melvin Baldwin, Ivan Balen, Ed Baley, John Balinski, Frank Balkis, Bob Ball, Charles Ball, K.D. Ball, Richard Ball, Robert Ball, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Prisoner description cards: Charles Ballard, Clyde Ballard, Jack Ballard, Ralph Ballard, Roscoe "Russell" Ballard, Lewis Ballew, Stephen Balliet, A.H. Bellnane, Joe Baltazor, Neevle Balton, Peter James Baltzer, Samuel Banchomb, Norris Bancroft, Jacob Bangart (Daniel Jonathan Bangart), George Bangert, George Bangesser, A.L. Banks, Adrian LeRoy Banks, William Banning, N. Bannon, Louis Bappre, Joe Barajos, C.C. Barbee, B.P. Barber, Earl Barber, O.P. Barber, William Barber [2 different ones], Frank Barcello, George Washington Barclay, Truman Barclay, J.W. Bardeaux (Peter Slater), Al Barden, James Henry Barden, Jenaro Ramides Barerras, Zella Barette (June Bramsen Barette), Frank Barg, Rade Barich, U.S. Bariel, Bryant Barker, Carroll Robert Barker (Carroll Robert Stockton), Herman Barker (B. Lavender), John T. Barker, Kenneth LeRoy Barker, Norman Barker, Marvin Barkley, John Barkstrom, Alexander Barlow, George Barnaby, Leo Barnaby, Peter J. Barnaby, George Barnard, Paul Barnell, Arnold Barnes, Charles Barnes [2 different ones], Fred C. Barnes, Fred DeMoui Barnes, Herbert Barnes, Lewis Barnes, Rex Barnes, W.R. Barnes,Wesley Barnes, Clarence Barnett, E.M. Barnett, Harry Barnett, J.J. Barnett, Fred Barnhard, Joe Barnhard, Charles Barnhart, Calvert Barnhisel, Roy Barnes, Kenneth Barnum, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Prisoner description cards: Matt Baron, Charles Barr, James Barr, Powell Barr, Robert Barr, W.J. Barr, Benjamin Barraza, Louis Barrera, A.J. Barrett, J.W. Barrett, John Edward Barrett, Martin E. Barrett, Pat Barrett, Joe Barrios, William Barron, Charles Barrows, Clifford Barry, Dan Barry, Frank Barry (F.E. Walsh), Fred Barry, G.F. Barry, James Barry, Jerry Barry, Michael Barry, William Barry, William C. Barry, Jack Barth, John Bartholomeu, Martin (William) Bartinoscke, Cal Bartlett, Charles Bartlett [2 different ones], George Bartley, Willie Bartley, Charles Barton, Frank Barton, W.W. Barton, Champion Bartron, Lloyd Woodrow Bartu, Robert Bartz, John Bartzen [Bartsen?], 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Prisoner description cards: Joe Basconi, Avergo Basilio, Harold Basney, Ricardo Basques, Charles Basschew, Edward Bassford, Tom Bastas, Edwin Bastian, Frank Bastian, Frank Bastien, Rueben Bastrom, Kenneth Batcheller, S.C. Bateman, Ernest Bates, Harvey Bates, James Bates, W.G. Bates, Charles Bathurst, Wesley Batters, Eugene Battle, H.D. Bauer, James Bauer, John Bauer, Otto Bauer, Raymond Bauer, Robert Baugh, Albert Baughman (Albert Morhin), Donald Baumann, Herman Bausch, A.H. Bauser, Elmo Baxter, Sherman Baxter, Steve Baxter, Willie Baxter, Eddie Bayless, Rex Baylass, Charles Bazel, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Prisoner description cards: George Beach, R.E. Beach, Samuel Beach, John Beadle, Walter Beakey, H.W. Beal, Arthur Beale, Henry Beals, Jack Beaman, Alvin Bean, Leo Bean, Benny Bear, Archie Bear Ground, Adam Bearcub, James Beard, Payton Beard, Ronald Beard, William Beard, J.M. Beardsley, Andrew Jackson Beare, Joe Bearwalker, W.H. Beasley, Clinton Beattie, Alonzo Beaty, William Beaty, Harry Beauchamp, Willard Beauchamp, Fred Beaudry, Hector Beaudry, Joe Beaudry, Raymond Beaudry, Alex Beauerin, Roland Beuregard, Francis Beaver, Melvin Beavers, Walter Beavers, Wecolm Bebout, Paul Bechant, Frank Bechiniski, 1910-1955 (Box-folder 6/6)